בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף daf is ה. Heh. We
pick up in the middle of ד עמוד ב, Daled Amud Bet,
the two dots about ten lines down. So we have to cover
some distance today to catch up, but hopefully it'll go relatively quickly.
כיצד כיצד: Keitzad Keitzad: חל להיות בשני בשבת. chal lihyot besheni beshabbat.
So the משנה Mishnah is working through the variations of how you
get it to be on the 12th, 13th, and 14th. So if
פורים Purim falls out on a Monday, כפרים ועיירות גדולות קוראים בו
ביום. kfarim ve'ayarot gedolot korim bo bayom. So the villages and the
cities read on Monday because it's a Monday. It's only an issue
when it's a non-Monday or non-Thursday. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
"Who's making that noise? Oh, okay good." So the גמרא Gemara says,
"Got it. מאי שנא רישא דנקט סידורא דירחא ומאי שנא סיפא דנקט
סידורא דיומא? Mai shna reisha de'nakat sidura deyarcha u'mai shna seifa de'nakat
sidura deyoma? Why does the beginning of the משנה Mishnah say 12,
13, 14 and talking about the day of the month, and then
when it starts giving the examples, it talks about the day of
the week that it falls out on? Does it fall out on
a Monday? Does it fall out on a Tuesday? Does it fall
out on a Wednesday? Right? Why not say in this case it'll
be
12, in this case 13, follow the same order of the month
rather than switching to the week to the day of the week?"
So the גמרא Gemara says no. אידי דמיהפכי ליה נקט סידורא דיומא.
Aidi demitpachei lei nakat sidura deyoma. If you would go by the
day of the month, you would have to work reverse in the
week. If you said, "Well, it's going to be on the 12th
when פורים Purim falls out on a Sunday, and it's going to
be on the 13th when פורים Purim falls out on a, you
know, whatever, on a שבת Shabbos or on a Friday." So you
would have to work back, so the order would be a non-logical
order because you'd be working backwards in the days of the week.
It's a lot easier to talk about which day of the week
it is and then to do the math that way rather than
to reverse the math. Okay. חל להיות בערב שבת. chal lihyot be'erev
shabbat. Now if it falls out on a Friday, so it says
that the big cities are on the 15th, the big cities and
the walled cities are on the 15th because you're not going to
read on שבת Shabbos on שבת, Shabbos, and the villages are on
the 14th. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתניתין מני? Matnitin
mani? Who's our משנה? Mishnah? אי רבי אי רבי יוסי. Ei Rabbi
ei Rabbi Yosi. It could be רבי, Rabbi, it could be רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi because we're going to see there's a debate of
תנאים Tannaim and רבי Rabbi and רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi position would
be consistent with the משנה. Mishnah.
מוקפים חומה Mukafim choma which are the next day. That's what I
said.
Okay. It could be no, the if it's on Friday, so on
Friday you read the big cities and the walled cities, and the
villages read on Thursday. So that position is either רבי Rabbi or
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, but it's going to be debated in a
ברייתא braisa and it's not all the תנאים. Tannaim. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. מתניתין מני? Matnitin mani? Who's our משנה? Mishnah?
אי רבי אי רבי יוסי. Ei Rabbi ei Rabbi Yosi. It could
be רבי, Rabbi, it could be רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi because we're
going to see there's a debate of תנאים Tannaim and רבי Rabbi
and רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi position would be consistent with the משנה.
Mishnah. מאי רבי? Mai Rabbi? Which is the where which רבי Rabbi
are you referring to? דתניא: De'tanya: we taught in a ברייתא. braisa.
This is the way of introducing ברייתות braitot that show that the
point of the משנה Mishnah is actually debated. Okay. דתניא: De'tanya: we
taught in a ברייתא. braisa. חל להיות בערב שבת: chal lihyot be'erev
shabbat:
the 14th falls out on Friday. כפרים ועיירות גדולות מקדימין ליום הכניסה.
Kfarim ve'ayarot gedolot makdimin leyom haknisah. So according to this ברייתא, braisa,
it says that the cities and the villages both read on a
Thursday. ומוקפים חומה קורין בו ביום. U'mukafim choma korim bo bayom.
And the walled cities read on the Friday. So pretty much nobody
reads on the right time. Okay. The walled cities read on the
Friday which is the 14th, and the big cities read on Thursday
which is the 13th. The logic for that, as the גמרא Gemara
will explain, is you cannot have that this position holds the more
important thing is that the walled cities and read on a different
day than everybody else. Read on a different day than the larger
cities. Okay. Because the as the גמרא Gemara says, the תורה Torah
says אכן הפרזים בערי הפרזות Achen haprazim be'arei haprazot and it's contrasting
open cities with walled cities. Those always have to be different. So
since you can't read the walled cities on שבת, Shabbos, you're going
to have to read them on Friday. But if you're reading them
on Friday, you can no longer have in the big cities to
continue to be on Friday, so then you're going to have to
push up to push back to Thursday. Okay, so that starts with
that principle that you have to keep 14 and 15 distinct. So
that's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. And then רבי Rabbi says the
position of our משנה. Mishnah. רבי אומר: Rabbi omer: רבי Rabbi says,
אומר אני: Omer ani: I disagree. I say, לא ידחו העיירות ממקומם.
lo yidachu hayayarot mimkomam.
The big cities stay where they are. They're on Friday on the
14th. אלא אלו ואלו קוראים בו ביום. Ela elu ve'elu korim bo
bayom. So you have the walled cities and the big cities on
the same day, they'll both be on a Friday.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara spells out the different reasons. מאי
טעמא דתנא קמא? Mai ta'ama de'tanna kamma? What's the motivating issue for
the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? דכתיב בכל שנה ושנה. De'chtiv be'chol shana
veshana. That it should be this way every year. להיות עושים את
שני ימי הפורים האלה בכל שנה ושנה. Lihyot osim et shenei yemei
hapurim ha'eleh be'chol shana veshana. And they're two separate days. מה בכל
שנה ושנה עיירות קודמות למוקפים. Ma be'chol shana veshana ayrot kodmos lemukafim.
The same way the general rule is that the unwalled cities precede
the walled cities, אף כאן עיירות קודמות למוקפים: af kan ayrot kodmos
lemukafim: here too, the unwalled have to precede the walled. So if
the walled are going to have to be on on Friday the
14th, so the unwalled will have to be the day before. So
ואימא: ve'eima: but the גמרא Gemara says,
but there's another issue at stake here. בכל שנה ושנה: Be'chol shana
veshana: it should be like it is every year. מה בכל שנה
ושנה אין נדחים העיירות ממקומם: Ma be'chol shana veshana ein nidachim hayayarot
mimkomam: the same way in a normal year you do not move
the date of... of the unwalled cities, unless there's like a really
compelling reason like if it's on שבת, Shabbos, but the general rule
is you don't move the date of the unwalled cities, those are
the 14th, אף כאן לא ידחו ממקומן. af kan lo yidachu mimkoman.
So here too maybe we should say keep it on the 14th
and let the chips fall where they may so it'll be the
same date as the walled city.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני הכא דלא אפשר. shani hacha
d'lo efshar. Okay, that's true, there are a lot of things we
do every year. The question is, which one has to give? So
here, it's not possible to keep the 14th on the right day
because the more important principle is 15th and 14th have to be
different days. Okay, so for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that is
the more important principle, keeping 14 and 15 distinct. The רבי, Rebbi,
and רבי Rebbi obviously has a different principle that's more important. מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama,
what's his reason? בכל שנה ושנה, bekhol shana v'shana,
the same way we like to keep the unwalled cities in their
regular place on the 14th. It's not that we never change it
but that's what we want to prioritize. אף כאן לא ידחו ממקומן,
af kan lo yidachu mimkoman, here too you keep them on the
14th and if that results in the walled and the unwalled reading
on the same day, both reading on Friday the 14th, let so
let it be. ואימא, veima, the גמרא Gemara says how about the
other principle: בכל שנה ושנה מה כל שנה ושנה עיירות קודמות למוקפין
אף כאן נמי עיירות קודמות למוקפין. bekhol shana v'shana ma kol shana
v'shana ayarot kodmot l'mukafin af kan nami ayarot kodmot l'mukafin. How about
the general idea that the unwalled precede the walled cities? No, שאני
הכא דלא אפשר. shani hacha d'lo efshar. Okay, but you can't do
that here because, you know, you got to choose between your principles.
Is it basically going to be let's keep the 14th, let's keep
the unwalled before the walled, that's the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, or
let's not move the 14th unless absolutely necessary and that's רבי Rebbi
and that's the position of our משנה. Mishna.
That's what לא אפשר lo efshar means is, does לא אפשר lo
efshar mean it would go into שבת Shabbos and it's not a
walled city and that's something like that?
No, that's why you have to move the 15th but that's not
לא אפשר lo efshar to move the 14th, you can just move
the 14th back to the 13th which is what the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma does. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says so that's anyway
the opinion of our משנה, Mishna, but the גמרא Gemara is pointing
out that according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of this ברייתא
Baraisa there's another possibility: have the, you know, move the 15th and
the 14th to keep those on separate days. מאי רבי יוסי? mai
Rebbi Yossi? Now where's the רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi that also holds
like רבי? Rebbi? But introducing רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi will also introduce
a third possibility of what to do in this Friday scenario. דתניא,
detanya, we תנא tana a ברייתא: Baraisa: חל להיות בערב שבת, chal
lihyot b'erev Shabbos, it falls out on a Friday, מוקפין וכפרים מקדימין
ליום הכניסה. mukafin u'kfarim makdimin l'yom haknesiah.
So walled cities and the villages go back to a Thursday. So
listen to this possibility: we're going to keep, we're going to keep
the 14th on the day, we won't move that unless it's absolutely
necessary, so the unwalled cities stay in the 14th, but I also
agree that walled cities and unwalled shouldn't be on the same day.
So what am I going to do? I'm not, I'm going to
have them go all the way back to Thursday. The walled cities
and the villages will be on Thursday so at least it'll keep
the walled and the unwalled distinct.
Alright, they read before, they read before the
unwalled.
Right. ועיירות גדולות קוראות בו ביום. v'ayarot gdolot korot bo bayom. רבי
יוסי אומר אין מוקפין קודמין לעיירות. Rebbi Yossi omer ein mukafin kodmin
l'ayarot. No, come on, you cannot have the walled cities come before
the unwalled, especially if you think about the irony, right, because the
whole point is that the walled cities' miracle continued further. So to
say the walled cities have a celebration on the 14th, okay, you
know, the primary victory occurred on the 14th even in שושן. Shushan.
So it makes sense to have, I mean it occurred on the
13th, they celebrate on the 14th, you know, so the 14th is
at least relevant for שושן, Shushan, right? But to go all the
way earlier, you know, that seems to make no sense.
Just the reading as opposed to also the other things we do
like the מצוות mitzvos of the day.
Um, so that's a good point. We're going to get to the
issue of the other מצוות mitzvos of the day and you're right
that, you know, this is specifically about the reading of it so
you don't have to necessarily make the big argument that the whole
יום yom is only is, you know, is not relevant. It's a
good point. But still you would want the reading to correspond to,
you know, some significance.
The formalism is undermining the content.
Exactly. That's a good point. ועיירות גדולות. v'ayarot gdolot. So the גמרא
Gemara רבי יוסי אומר אין מוקפין קודמין לעיירות Rebbi Yossi omer ein
mukafin kodmin l'ayarot אלא אלו ואלו קורין בו ביום ela elu v'elu
korin bo bayom like our משנה. Mishna. 14th and 15th read on
Friday and the villages read on Thursday. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
just spells out what clearly are the principles here. מאי טעמא דתנא
קמא? mai ta'ama deTanna Kamma? דכתיב בכל שנה ושנה dechtiv bekhol shana
v'shana like every year, מה כל שנה ושנה עיירות בארבעה עשר וזמנו
של זה לא זמנו של זה. ma kol shana v'shana ayarot b'arba'a
asar v'zmano shel zeh lo zmano shel zeh. The same way in
general we try to keep the big cities on the 14th six
and we try to keep the walled and the unwalled on different
days, not necessarily one preceding the other, but at least different days.
So here too So אף כאן עיירות בארבעה עשר וזמנו של זה
לא זמנו של זה af kan ayarot b'arba'a asar v'zmano shel zeh
lo zmano shel zeh even if it means having the 15th go
earlier and go on a Thursday. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא
בכל שנה ושנה מה כל שנה ושנה אין מוקפין קודמין לעיירות. veima
bekhol shana v'shana ma kol shana v'shana ein mukafin kodmin l'ayarot. Why
don't we say, look, but the general rule is that in every
year, even maybe we don't
have to say the walled city always comes after the the unwalled,
but at least they never come before the unwalled. אף כאן אין
מוקפין קודמין לעיירות. af kan ein mukafin kodmin l'ayarot. Here too let's
say they don't come before. שאני הכא דלא אפשר. shani hacha d'lo
efshar. Look, we don't have all of our choices available here, something's
gotta give. So I'd rather keep make them earlier in order to
keep them distinct.
מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי? mai ta'ama deRebbi Yossi? What's the reason of
רבי יוסי? Rebbi Yossi? Like we said
before בכל שנה ושנה. bekhol shana v'shana. No for me, I'm not
going to let the walled, they might be on the same day
as the unwalled, but they're not going to be before the unwalled,
אף כאן Af kan אי ee מוקפין mukfin קודם kodem לפרזים. l'perazim.
ואימא בכל שנה ושנה Ve'eima bechol shana veshana מה כל שנה ושנה
ma kol shana veshana זמנו של זה לא כזמנו של זה. zmano
shel ze lo kezmano shel ze. How about the idea of keeping
them as distinct days? אף כאן Af kan זמנו של זה לא
כזמנו של זה. zmano shel ze lo kezmano shel ze. Here too
let's keep them as distinct days. Gemara says no, שאני shani הכא
hacha דלא d'lo אפשר. efshar. Here there's no option. Okay, meaning that
no option but you gotta choose between bad options so nothing that
he likes exactly. Okay now I do think that the interesting thing
that emerges from this, and I'm not going to sort of give
an answer right now but I want you to think about, I
mean I have an answer, but I want you to sort of
think about and grapple with is you know the big, one of
the big חידושים chiddushim of the
מגילה Megilla and how this מסכת masechet institutionalizes it. Like the מגילה
Megilla just mentions you know what happened in שושן, Shushan, that שושן
Shushan had an extra day, and it says the פרזים perazim keep
the 14th and it never says what the non-פרזים perazim keep, right?
So it's not even so explicit although it does say 14th and
15th, okay maybe everybody would have had a שושן פורים, Shushan Purim,
who knows? Anyway, but what our משנה mishna and what חזל Chazal
do, they institutionalize the idea of different days of פורים Purim and
we don't have that by any other חג, chag, right? I mean
we have two days of יום טוב Yom Tov in חוץ לארץ,
Chutz l'Aretz, but fundamentally different days of a חג. chag. The whole
idea as I've said before is that you know one of the
things that unifies the people is that they all keep the same
type of like liturgical calendar, right? Difference between like Eastern Orthodox you
know and Western Christianity you know is different calendars of the holidays
and so on and how you keep your calendar. So the idea
that you're dividing the people into two separate days you know could
seem like as like, a, you have to explain why, why did
we allow that to happen, isn't that a bad thing? But then
it almost is like we are reinforcing it, right? We're making even
multiple different days, 13th, 11th, 12th etc. So that you could actually
say maybe that doesn't reinforce it, maybe it actually helps like if
there's a lot of options, it's not like we're two separate people,
the walled cities and the unwalled cities, it's like there are a
lot of possible days that we could read. But it's interesting to
think how we increase the options and here too the positions that
say I'm going to insist that you keep 14th and 15th distinct
whether it's by making, you know, this however it's going to be
done, but there are two opinions here that are insisting whether it's
by making one earlier whether it's pushing both days, we have to
keep them distinct, we don't like the idea that they should be
together. I think it raises a very fascinating question like shouldn't that
be a good, like certainly not a bad thing, you know that
it's possible that we all going to celebrate on the same day?
So I do want to have, we don't פסקן pasken that way
in this case, right? In this case we פסקן pasken that they
will read on the same day, that's our משנה, mishna, that's רבי,
Rebbi, okay, that they both read on Thursday but I do think
it's something to certainly think about. Yes Sally.
I think before we get into all the details of it just
the basic system of rabbinic law calendarizing events. Mm-hmm. This is just
the way that, you know, if the חטא העגל chet ha'egel and
the מרגלים meraglim have to be assigned dates on the calendar, so
all the things that happen in the מגילה Megilla
have
to have a date and the more dates on the calendar the
better you know.
Aha, we like to have a calendar filled with dates. Full of
history. That's an interesting, that's an interesting point, like the whole fact
of okay we have all these summer months, well we have the
three weeks and that then leads us up to אלול Elul and
that then like there's like, right? We make a point of the
fact that מרחשון Marcheshvan doesn't have any days in it. So okay,
that's an interesting point, but I, but I, but I still think
the question about why would you want to insist that you keep
14th and 15th separate, right, is, oh so you're saying because you
want to have multiple dates? But here you're going to have multiple
dates anyway, you're going to have a Thursday and a Friday. The
question is just how do you distribute, which does the Thursday and
which does the Friday? So I still do think it's a relevant
question. Charlie, what did you want to say?
Yeah there's one other case where things are read on different days
when first day of שבועות Shavuot falls on Friday there's several weeks
where the תורה Torah readings differ between Israel and the diaspora.
Yeah but that's not, that's true but but again that's not so
much like of a חג chag you know and but but there
are those differences, that is true. Okay so let's continue. Anyway just
to me definitely something that's very distinct about מגילה Megilla is the
separation of the celebrations. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, where are we, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, וסבר V'savar רבי Rebbi דחיינהו d'chayinhu ליום l'yom הכניסה? haknisah? Does
רבי Rebbi really hold that we're going to insist again unless it
falls out on שבת Shabbos but we're going to insist that the
that the unwalled cities are on the 14th and they don't get
pushed back to a
Monday-Thursday? והתניא, V'hatanya, but we taught in a ברייתא, braita, חל להיות
בשבת chal lihyot beShabbos when it comes out on שבת, Shabbos, כפרים
מקדימין ליום הכניסה kfarim makdimin l'yom haknisah so the villages go back
to the Thursday, עיירות גדולות קורין בערב שבת ayarot gedolot korin be'erev
Shabbos and the big cities read on Friday, ומוקפות חומה למחר umukfot
choma lemachar and of course the walled cities are Sunday because that's
their natural day. Okay, רבי Rebbi אומר, omer, so that's okay, you
can't do it on שבת, Shabbos, you got to do it on
Friday, all's well and good but רבי Rebbi says, אומר אני omer
ani I hold... הואיל ונידחו עיירות ממקומן, ho'il venidchu ayaros mimkoman, since
you're already moving the unwalled cities from their from their fixed day,
you're pushing them back from שבת Shabbos to Friday, ידחו ליום הכניסה.
yidchu leyom haknisa. You might as well push them all the way
back to Thursday and make life more convenient on people and have
everybody read, everybody in the unwalled, read on the same day, everybody
read on a read on Thursday. So you see he's willing to
move it back to a Thursday, so why wouldn't he, when it
fell out on a Friday, why was he unwilling to move it
back to a Thursday? So the answer is obvious. הכי השתא, Hachi
Hashta, how could you compare those cases? התם זמן שבת היא. Hasam
zman Shabbos hi. There, the fourteenth fell out on a שבת, Shabbos,
והואיל ונידחו ידחו. veho'il venidchu yidchu. Like רבי Rebbi says, if you're
already moving the day, so we'll move it to Thursday, that's more
convenient. והכא, V'hacha, in the case we were talking about, זמן ערב
שבת, zman Erev Shabbos, it was a Friday. So, and when it's,
when you're able to keep it on its regular day, he's not
going to move it to Thursday just to make life easier. Okay.
כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבי חלבו, K'man azla ha d'amar Rebbi Chelbo,
who is it going like that which, that which רבי חלבו Rebbi
Chelbo taught? אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, בשם רב הונא, b'shem
Rav Huna, פורים שחל להיות בשבת, Purim shechal lihyos b'Shabbos, הכל נדחין
ליום הכניסה. hakol nidchin leyom haknisa. So, when פורים Purim falls out
on שבת, Shabbos, everybody is going to be on Thursday. So הכל
נדחין סלקא דעתך? Hakol nidchin salka deitach? Really everybody? והאיכא מוקפין דעבדי
במחר? Ve'ika mukafin d'avdi b'machar? What about the walled cities? They're going
to do on Sunday. Why should they move? אלא הכל הנידח, Ela
hakol hanidach, ידחה ליום הכניסה. yidche leyom haknisa. Anybody that we're going
to be moving, we're going to move back to Thursday. So כמאן
כרבי, K'man k'Rebbi, that's like רבי. Rebbi. If you're already moving the
fourteenth from שבת, Shabbos, you might as well push it back to
Thursday. And I would point out that again, like רבי Rebbi in
the משנה, Mishnah, that has the benefit of minimizing the distribution of
days, right? Might as well if we're able to
collapse the כפרים kefarim and the עיירות, ayaros, we might as well.
So it seems like רבי Rebbi does not find it problematic to
keep to overlap days and sometimes maybe even prefers that. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: דכולי עלמא מיהא, Dechulei alma
miha, everybody nonetheless, clearly the assumption of our entire משנה, Mishnah, all
these ברייתות, Braytos, is מגילה בשבת לא קרינן, Megilla b'Shabbos lo karinan,
we can't read the מגילה Megilla on שבת. Shabbos. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? It's never explained why not. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, famous
statement of רבא, Rava, הכל חייבין בקריאת מגילה, hakol chayavin bikrias Megilla,
everybody's obligated to read
the
מגילה, Megilla, and ואין הכל בקיאין במקרא מגילה, ve'ein hakol baki'in b'mikra
Megilla, but not everybody knows how to read it. So here you
are at home, you own a מגילה Megilla presumably, but you don't
know how to read it for yourself. So גזירה שמא יטלנה בידו,
gezira shema yitlena beyado, וילך אצל בקי ללמוד, v'yeilech etzel baki lilmod,
you'll go, you'll take it in your hand, you'll go over to
your next-door neighbor, he knows how to read or he'll teach me
how to read, ויעבירנו ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים, v'ya'avirenu arba amos b'reshus
harabbim, and you'll come to carry it, okay, which is a little
funny because if you have somebody else in the town who knows
how to read presumably they own a מגילה, Megilla, but not
necessarily. Maybe he's not wealthy enough to own a מגילה. Megilla. He
knows how to read. Like a lot of people I think know
how to read but don't necessarily own a מגילה, Megilla, so you'll
wind up carrying your מגילה Megilla to that person. והיינו, V'hainu, now
that's all רבא Rava says. Then it's important to recognize that the
next line is introduced by the סתם Stam of the גמרא Gemara
because you see the shift to Aramaic,
והיינו טעמא דשופר והיינו טעמא דלולב. V'hainu ta'ama d'shofar v'hainu ta'ama d'lulav.
Oh, the same reason is for שופר shofar and לולב, lulav, because
שופר shofar and לולב lulav we know are two other days that
you do not, two other things that you will not do on
שבת. Shabbos. Okay, now the thing to notice is is that and
when we learned מסכת סוכה, Masechet Sukkah, we discussed this and מסכת
ראש השנה, Masechet Rosh Hashanah, it's possible maybe שופר shofar and לולב
lulav there's other reasons why you don't do it on
שבת. Shabbos. שופר shofar the גמרא Gemara quotes a פסוק passuk about
זכרון תרועה, zichron teruah, יום תרועה, yom teruah, the idea that even
if it's not a מלאכה melacha but still there's some sense of
a violation of שבת, Shabbos, that type of a thing. Who knows
what the other reasons are, but all of this comes from רבא
Rava made one claim about the reason by מגילה Megilla and then
the גמרא Gemara expands that to all these other three cases. All
we know from the תנא-itic Tanna material is you don't do these
things on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, and our assumption that oh the reason
you don't do it is because we're afraid you'll come to carry
is all based on a statement רבא Rava makes by מגילה Megilla
that gets expanded by the סתם Stam of the גמרא Gemara to
the other cases. הירושלמי Yerushalmi does not necessarily, certainly by שופר, shofar,
and does not necessarily buy in that that's the only reason, or
that that is the reason why these things are not done on
שבת. Shabbos. Just one minute, and I want to even show you
that the next line of the גמרא Gemara suggests at least another
reason for מגילה. Megilla. So the גמרא Gemara says, רב יוסף אמר,
Rav Yosef amar, מפני שעיניהם של עניים נשואות במקרא מגילה. mipnei she'eineihem
shel aniyim nesuos b'mikra Megilla.
Because you read the מגילה, Megilla, it says מתנות לאביונים, matanos l'evyonim,
and you have all the poor in the שול shul and they're
this is like the greatest opportunity, they want to put their hands
out. But it's שבת, Shabbos, I'm sorry, I can't give. Somebody once
commented to me, like he says, the difference in terms of like
in synagogues as opposed to in churches, says never underestimate the power
of being able to pass around the collection
plate after the sermon, right? In a synagogue, you cannot pass around
the collection plate after the sermon, it's שבת. Shabbos. So you can
talk about the importance of צדקה tzedaka or whatever you're talking about
but then you can't go ahead and have people immediately act on
it. So here you're reading the מגילה, Megilla, what a great opportunity.
opportunity for people, for the עניים aniyim to say,
okay, מתנות לאביונים. matanos l'evyonim. נו, Nu, and if you don't do
it on that day, they're gonna wind up getting a lot less
and they're certainly going to feel despair, despair at the time of
the reading of the מגילה. Megillah. So a very different reason, nothing
to do with carrying. So what does he think the reason is
for שופר shofar and לולב? lulav? Who knows? We'll figure out what
that reason is, but nothing to do with carrying. Now תוספות Tosafos
is not happy with the idea that that there could be this
reason that's not based on carrying. If you look at תוספות, Tosafos,
רב יוסף רב יוסף אמר משום שעיניהם נשואות למקרא מגילה, Rav Yosef
Rav Yosef amar mishum she'eineihem nesuos lemikra Megillah, תוספות Tosafos says, על
כרחך צריך לומר דרב יוסף לא פליגי אטעמא דרבה. al karchach tzarich
lomar deRav Yosef lo pligi ata'ama deRabbah. He doesn't really argue on
the reason of carrying. תא גבי שופר ולולב ליכא טעמא אחרינא. ta
gabi shofar v'lulav leika ta'ama achrina. There's no other reason for שופר
shofar and לולב. lulav. מכל מקום קמה הכא טעמא אחרינא. mikol makom
kama hacha ta'ama achrina. There's another reason here as well, etc. Okay,
but that's not necessarily פשט. pshat. The גמרא Gemara is the one
that extended רבה Rabbah to שופר shofar and לולב. lulav. רב יוסף
Rav Yosef has a different reason of מגילה, Megillah, maybe he has
a different reason, maybe there's a different reason for שופר shofar and
לולב lulav as well. Yes, David, you had a question?
But the reason of carrying apply to a walled city?
In a walled city, oh that's an excellent point. Yes, the walled
city there's no problem of carrying. So why, so that's an excellent
point. So according to רבה, Rabbah, what's the whole issue of a
walled city not doing it on שבת? Shabbos?
Yeah, especially because we're going to see later that it has to
have really walls on all four sides. Now it is possible that
you have a walled city and you didn't make like, you know,
an עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, but then we're dealing with a דרבנן
d'rabonan problem. You know, or you could have a walled city that
has so much, the גמרא Gemara says like if the doors of
ירושלים Yerushalayim weren't locked at night then that would create a רשות
הרבים reshus harabim even in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but still the likelihood is
much, much rarer. It's an excellent point. Like to the, you know,
'cause you can't say like לא פלוג, lo plug, the whole category
is walled cities. I don't know. People must talk about it. I'll
have to look that up. That's a great question. Okay, so that
at least, and clearly you move the walled cities from the 14th
as well. You know, so תוספות Tosafos might answer, well, that's why
רב יוסף Rav Yosef gives an additional reason. He reads it as
an additional, not an alternative. Okay, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, אף על פי שאמרו כפרים מקדימין ליום הכניסה, af
al pi she'amru kefarim makdimin leyom hakenisah,
and this is going to support רב יוסף Rav Yosef's idea about
the importance of having מתנות לאביונים matanos l'evyonim the same day of
the reading of the מגילה. Megillah. Even though they said that the
villages do it on a Monday and the Thursday, the general early
reading, גובין בו ביום ומחלקין בו ביום. govin bo bayom umachalkin bo
bayom.
That the other thing we put off, Michael's asking, it's just the
מקרא מגילה Mikra Megillah we put off. How about the סעודה, Seudah,
right? How about the other מצוות, mitzvos, משלוח מנות? mishloach manos? So
here we're seeing that the מתנות לאביונים matanos l'evyonim is coupled with
the מקרא מגילה Mikra Megillah exactly for this reason of you're reading
in the, in the מגילה מתנות לאביונים, Megillah matanos l'evyonim, you have
to act on it. You do not want to create despair amongst
the עניים aniyim that they're hoping for it and not getting it.
Other point I made also, people hopefully will give more if they're
doing it immediately in response. So when you read the מגילה Megillah
early, you also do the מתנות לאביונים matanos l'evyonim early. Not only
do you collect it early, right, if the whole question is how
much will people give, maybe you collect it early but we'll distribute
it on פורים. Purim. No, that's the point, that the עניים aniyim
are now waiting for us. So not only do you collect it
on that day, you distribute it on that day as well. And
משלוח מנות mishloach manos would also that... So we'll get to that.
We're not, you know, that, so hold off on that, right? The
remaining questions are משלוח מנות mishloach manos and the
סעודה. Seudah. Okay, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly,
I'm sorry, no I read that. אף על פי שאמרו, af al
pi she'amru, okay. אף על פי שאמרו, af al pi she'amru, even
though they said you do it early, you collect early as well.
משום דאמרו הוא, mishum d'amru hu, it's because you're reading early, therefore
you collect early. It's not although. אלא, Ela, okay, fine, that's what
it means. הואיל ואמרו שכבר מקדימין ליום הכניסה, ho'il v'amru shekevar makdimin
leyom hakenisah, because they said you're going to read early on a
Monday, Thursday, גובין בו ביום ומחלקין בו ביום, govin bo bayom umachalkin
bo bayom, you also collect that day and distribute that day, מפני
שעיניהם של עניים נשואות במקרא מגילה, mipnei she'eineihem shel aniyim nesuos bemikra
Megillah, because the עניים aniyim are looking, you know, to the reading
of the מגילה. Megillah. Everybody's going to be around, they're going to
be gathered, they're going to say מתנות לאביונים. matanos l'evyonim. Finally, now
is a great opportunity, people will actually give us some צדקה. tzedakah.
Okay, אבל, aval, going back to Michael's point, שמחה אינה נוהגת אלא
בזמנה. simcha einah noheges ela bizmanah. The rejoicing, meaning the סעודת פורים,
Seudas Purim, that is only in the right time. That only is
on the actual date, the 14th or the 15th. So it's the,
right, if they want to use the money for the סעודה, Seudah,
whatever. Anyway, the סעודה Seudah is only on the date, the real
date, not on the early date. This would also apply if you
read early because of שבת. Shabbos. So the remaining מצוה mitzvah we
didn't cover, מגילה Megillah would be early, מתנות לאביונים matanos l'evyonim goes
with מגילה, Megillah, סעודה Seudah goes בזמנה. bizmanah. So what's the one
thing we haven't dealt with? משלוח מנות. mishloach manos. So משלוח מנות
mishloach manos is basically understood to be you're sending מנות, manos, you're
sending food because that's going to be eaten at the סעודה. Seudah.
That's a way of sharing the סעודה. Seudah. So if מתנות לאביונים
matanos l'evyonim goes with מגילה, Megillah, משלוח מנות mishloach manos goes with
the סעודה Seudah and both of those are בו ביום. bo bayom.
Okay.
What's interesting is that you know, then you sort of have the
tension of שבת Shabbos and פורים Purim because you want to have
a nice סעודה Seudah for שבת Shabbos but if you're doing it
earlier you may not have as much for שבת Shabbos because you
know, these poor people, you know what I'm saying, depending on when
you do it. In other words, if we're saying that we're מקדימים
makdimim everything... Not מקדימים makdimim the סעודה.
seudah. What do you mean?
No, well, I'm sorry.
Well,
you're not מקדימים makdimim the סעודה. seudah. The סעודה seudah is on
the day that it falls. You're מקדימים makdimim with... you מקדימים makdimim
מקרא מגילה mikra megilla with מתנות לאביונים matanot la'evyonim and the סעודה
seudah משלוח מנות mishloach manot you keep on the day. Okay, it
doesn't say משלוח מנות mishloach manot but that's the assumption. All right.
Yes.
משלוח מנות mishloach manot requires you to take things from one place
to another.
Yeah, that's a very good point.
It's a very good point. Well this case of מקדימים... makdimim...
Right,
but his point is it does become quite ironic.
His point about the מקרא מגילה mikra megilla on the כרכים krakhim
and here the משלוח מנות. mishloach manot. So this case is... all
right, I gotta look into both of those. Excellent points. All right,
the גמרא gemara says like this: אמר רב amar Rav מגילה בזמנה
קורין אותה אפילו ביחיד שלא בזמנה בעשרה. megilla bizmanah korin otah afilu
beyachid shelo bizmanah ba'asarah.
So now we get to this פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa issue which
was so important we saw before about how weighty it is and
the inclusion of women and all these other issues. So here then
the question should come up if פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa is such
a central part of מקרא מגילה, mikra megilla, maybe you should need
to do it בציבור? betzibur? Right? And now you know we light
חנוכה chanukah candles and we say it's about פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa
we don't say it's בציבור, betzibur, but at least we say it
has to be in a place where it's visible and has to
be at a time when people are walking around the streets. So
maybe there has to be that element by מקרא מגילה mikra megilla
as well. So here the גמרא gemara introduces that possibility. אמר רב
amar Rav מגילה בזמנה קורין אותה אפילו ביחיד. megilla bizmanah korin otah
afilu beyachid. If you're reading it on the right time, it's not
an early date, then even an individual can read it. You can
read it even without the aspect of פרסומי ניסא... pirsumei nisa... well
let's take a look. You can read it even as a private
individual. שלא בזמנה, shelo bizmanah, not in its right time when you're
doing it like early Monday, Thursday, or whatever it is, בעשרה, ba'asarah,
you need ten people, you need it to be a, you know,
you need it to be פרסום נס ברבים. pirsum nes berabbim. By
the way, ten people, does that necessarily mean ten men and a
מניין minyan idea, or is the idea of רבים rabbim not the
same as מניין? minyan? It's not necessarily דברים שבקדושה, devarim shebekedusha, right?
You know the issues come up for example when we say as
a... well maybe it's not so radically different because events of the
time of מגילה... megilla... but anyway, if we say the idea... well
actually חנוכה chanukah rather... but anyway, you say the idea, what do
you call it? About קידוש השם, kiddush Hashem, right? That if it's
like ברבים, berabbim, you know, somebody has to martyr themselves ברבים berabbim
if there's certain cases, in certain cases.
So the פסק psak of the מהר"ם מרוטנבורג Maharam MiRothenburg is that's
not defined by ten men, right? The idea of רבים rabbim is
an idea of not דברים שבקדושה, devarim shebekedusha, it's an idea of
like many people. So anyway there's an interesting question about the idea
of רבים rabbim by מגילה megilla as well when there's this idea,
does it mean the sense of מניין minyan or how do you
define the ten? So that's number one, that point of בעשרה. ba'asarah.
But going back then to this... so it's about you know because
עשרה asarah as I'm saying could play a role of רבים rabbim
and could play a role of like דברים שבקדושה devarim shebekedusha which
is a sort of different type of role. But here there's this
difference if you're reading it שלא בזמנה shelo bizmanah it has to
דווקא davka have that element of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. So what's
the aspect when it's בזמנה? bizmanah? Does it not need פרסומי ניסא?
pirsumei nisa? So you could take it two ways. You could say,
you know, you could be מקיים mekayem it with פרסומי ניסא pirsumei
nisa and without פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. Obviously it's best to be
מקיים mekayem it with פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, but if you're already
doing it at the right time, you know, maybe technically you can
do it even without that element. We'll allow a part... it's like
the non-full קיום. kiyum. If already we're sort of compromising and having
it not at the right time and especially if you realize that
the reason we push it early is at a communal level. We
don't push it early at an individual level. We do it for
like a community, for the whole כפר, kfar, for the whole, for
the whole עיר, ir, right? That's why we're doing it early. So
then it also has to be, you know, sort of done at
that communal level. That's one way of reading it. רש"י Rashi tries
to say that if you're doing it at the right time you'll
always get פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. If you look at רש"י Rashi
בזמנה bizmanah top of the דף, daf, בי"ד be-Yud Dalet מתוך שחובה
בו ביום על כל יחיד ויחיד קורין אותה אפילו ביחיד דהכל קורין
בו ואיכא פרסום הנס. mitokh shechovah bo bayom al kol yachid veyachid
korin otah afilu beyachid dehakol korin bo ve'ika pirsum hanes. Since, since
this is the fixed time, everybody is going to read today, so
even if everybody is reading individually, maybe everybody is doing like a
פרסום הנס pirsum hanes for themselves. You know, I don't exactly get
it because you know if the whole village is reading early, then
all the villagers are, but maybe the difference is the villages reading
early but the town is not. So some of the people of
this current population are reading and some of this population are not
reading. That's not the same idea of a פרסום הנס pirsum hanes
if everybody in this population is involved in it even if they're
involved in it at the private level. So you can try to
sort of unpack that. But רש"י Rashi tries to claim that when
it's בזמנה bizmanah and presumably בזמנה bizmanah means everybody is you know
and therefore everybody is doing it, we don't have to worry about
whether you're performing it ברבים berabbim or ביחיד. beyachid. When it's שלא
בזמנה shelo bizmanah it requires more of the element of רבים. rabbim.
So that's the initial position. רב אסי אומר בין בזמנה בין שלא
בזמנה בעשרה. Rav Assi omer bein bizmanah bein shelo bizmanah ba'asarah. Whether
in its right time or not in its right time, you always
need עשרה, asarah, which means no, you always need this fuller element
of פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, right? It's by the way somewhat similar
to the whole issue of lighting חנוכה Chanukah candles inside the house
and not in the window. Can you have a פרסומי ניסא pirsumei
nisa for בני בית, bnei bayis, like a personal פרסומי ניסא? pirsumei
nisa? And he's saying no, you always need this פרסומי ניסא pirsumei
nisa going outside, going to other people, it always has to be
בציבור betzibur or ברבים. berabbim. הוי עובדא hava uvda
there was a case וחש ליה
לרב להא דרב אשי. ve-chash lei le-Rav le-ha de-Rav Ashi. There was
a case that it was read once שלא בזמנה, shelo bizmanah, and
maybe again it was being pushed earlier because of a שבת, Shabbos,
maybe it was a case of a village, and רב, Rav, although
he said that you need I'm sorry, no, excuse me, there was
a case where it was בזמנה, bizmanah, excuse me, it was a
case where it was בזמנה, bizmanah, and although רב Rav says בזמנה
bizmanah you could do it ביחיד, beyachid, רב Rav made a point
of being concerned for the position of רב אשי Rav Ashi and
trying to insist that he would do it ברבים. berabbim. So here,
sort of giving in terms of practice, he's inclined towards being מחמיר
machmir at least like רב אשי, Rav Ashi, always doing it ברבים.
berabbim. So ומי אמר רב הכי, u'mi amar Rav hachi, would רב
Rav really say that, to always push you to do it ברבים
berabbim even if it's a case of בזמנה? bizmanah? והאמר רב יהודה
בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב, ve-ha-amar Rav Yehuda bereih de-Rav
Shmuel bar Sheilas mishmeih de-Rav, פורים שחל להיות בשבת, Purim she-chal lihyos
be-Shabbos, so we have this teaching in the name of רב, Rav,
when פורים Purim falls out on שבת, Shabbos, ערב שבת זמנם. erev
Shabbos zmanam. So the time becomes Friday. So what does it mean
ערב שבת זמנם, erev Shabbos zmanam, their time is Friday? והשבת זמנם?
veha-Shabbos zmanam? No, the date is שבת, Shabbos, we might read it
early, but the date isn't Friday. אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar,
this must be what he
means. שלא בזמנם כזמנם, shelo bizmanam kezmanam, if we're not talking about
the villagers reading early, but we're shifting the whole date from a
שבת Shabbos to a Friday, then Friday has the status of זמנה.
zmanah. So what's the significance of having the status of זמנה? zmanah?
מה זמנם אפילו ביחיד, ma zmanam afilu beyachid, the same way when
it's normally on the right day you can do it
private, שלא בזמנם אפילו ביחיד, shelo bizmanam afilu beyachid, then שלא בזמנם
shelo bizmanam you could also do it ביחיד beyachid if the whole
day has shifted. Meaning, the idea, where do we see that it
matters whether you call something זמנה zmanah or not for מקרא מגילה,
mikra megillah, right? It only matters according to רב Rav that says
בזמנה bizmanah you can read it ביחיד beyachid and שלא בזמנה shelo
bizmanah you need to do it ברבים. berabbim. Otherwise we haven't seen
this concept of זמנה. zmanah. And now he says within רב Rav
there's two scenarios of שלא בזמנה. shelo bizmanah. There's the case where
the villagers read early, that's a real שלא בזמנה, shelo bizmanah, that's
when he says you need to do it ברבים, berabbim, as that
רש״י Rashi explains, part of the population is reading part is not.
There to get a פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa you have to do
it ברבים. berabbim. Then there's another case where the entire date, it
fell out on שבת Shabbos and for even for all the cities
the entire population is reading on Friday. That he says then Friday
becomes זמנה zmanah and therefore you can read it even ביחיד beyachid
because everybody is reading it on that day. It's not like a
split population like the villagers. So the גמרא Gemara says look, you
see that רב Rav is not going like רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
רב Rav is saying by his position that says that there's a
difference between זמנה zmanah and שלא בזמנה. shelo bizmanah. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, not necessarily. לענין מקרא מגילה בעשרה, le-inyan mikra megillah
ba-asarah, I could tell you that when it comes to reading of
the מגילה megillah רב Rav holds like רב אשי Rav Ashi and
whether it's זמנה zmanah whether it's not זמנה zmanah you always need
to do it with ten. אלא מאי ערב שבת זמנם, ela mai
erev Shabbos zmanam, so for what reason would we say Friday is
a זמן zman if the idea of זמנה zmanah isn't relevant for
the idea of whether you need ten people or not? So לאפוקי
מדרבי le-afokei mi-de-Rabbi to exclude the position of רבי, Rabbi, דאמר הואיל
ונדחו ידחו ליום הכניסה. de-amar ho'il ve-nidchu yidchu le-yom ha-kenisah.
רבי Rabbi says if you're moving it from שבת Shabbos already, don't
put it on Friday, put it all the way back to Thursday.
הא קמשמע לן דערב שבת זמנם הוא. ha ka-mashma lan de-erev Shabbos
zmanam hu. It's not telling you there's a conceptual difference between an
idea of זמנה zmanah and not זמנה, zmanah, it's a way of
underscoring, like it's a way of
pushing back against the position of רבי. Rabbi. רבי Rabbi says hey
you might as well push it, you might as well put it
to Thursday. No, Friday is the right time, not Thursday. So it
really is not coming to tell you anything of halachic import, it's
just coming to underscore that it's rejecting the position of רבי. Rabbi.
So in the end we're left with the fact that רב Rav
says that שלא בזמנה, shelo bizmanah, certainly when the case is a
split population, like the villagers are reading in a different day than
the townspeople, רב Rav everyone agrees you need to do it ברבים.
berabbim. בזמנה bizmanah is a debate, but in the end רב Rav
is inclined to go like רב אשי Rav Ashi and the גמרא
Gemara wants to interpret רב Rav consistent with רב אשי Rav Ashi
that would say even בזמנה bizmanah you need to do it ברבים.
berabbim. Now that's not our practice. So רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
both insist that based on another גמרא Gemara it's clear that you
could be יוצא ביחיד. yotzei beyachid. But what this is doing, the
position of רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying that that's really like
a בדיעבד bedi'eved way of fulfilling it. That's true, you can be
יוצא ביחיד, yotzei beyachid, but it's not just like I can דאוון
davven ביחיד, beyachid, I can not be on the ציבור, tzibur, it's
better to דאוון בציבור, davven betzibur, but it's not like a בדיעבד
bedi'eved דאוונינג davvening ביחיד, beyachid, although don't tell other people
that, but that's like that I get a higher קיום kiyum if
I do it בציבור. betzibur. Here it's different. Fundamentally you say the
מצוה mitzvah is about פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa and fundamentally it starts
ברבים. berabbim. But it is true that if you didn't do it
ברבים berabbim you could still be יוצא yotzei to the point that
look at תוספות, Tosafos, he says הוי עובדא וחש ליה לרב להא
דרב אשי, hava uvda ve-chash lei le-Rav le-ha de-Rav Ashi, so תוספות...
Tosafos... So תוספות Tosfos says מכל מקום הלכתא כוותיה דרב. mikol makom
hilchesa k'vasi d'Rav. First of all we rule like רב, Rav, and
then he goes about the first version of רב Rav that בזמנו
bizmano you can do it ביחיד, biyachid, and he carries on. And
ועוד, v'od, now I'm like two lines down in the narrow lines,
middle of the lines, ועוד, v'od, דרב אסי תלמיד רב הוי. d'Rav
Asi talmid Rav havei. I'm sorry. He says like this. רבינו יוסף
Rabbeinu Yosef where the asterisk is, איש ירושלים Ish Yerushalayim or this,
פסק pasak דאף ביחיד צריך לברך. d'af biyachid tzarich l'varech. וכן נמצא
בתשובת רש"י, ve-chein nimtza bitshuvat Rashi, שכתב נראה בעיני דלא שנא יחיד
ולא שנא ציבור אחד מברך ורבים שומעים, she-kasav nireh b'einai d'lo shna
yachid v'lo shna tzibur echad mivarech v'rabim shomim, וכן נראה ve-chein nireh
etc. So תוספות Tosfos even has a הוה אמינא hava amina that
when you're doing it ביחיד biyachid you don't make the ברכה. bracha.
Now you could say maybe you don't make the ברכה bracha of
שעשה נסים she-asa nissim because you don't have the פרסום הנס pirsum
hanes aspect. Maybe he's not questioning the other ברכות, brachos, but it
seems like תוספות Tosfos is questioning maybe all the ברכות brachos shouldn't
be made when you're doing it ביחיד. biyachid. Maybe there's a real
type of a בדיעבד bedieved fulfillment and doesn't even deserve the ברכה
bracha of על מקרא מגילה, al mikra megillah, but minimally it might
not deserve the ברכה bracha of שעשה נסים she-asa nissim because it
might be lacking in a significant way the פרסום הנס pirsum hanes
component. So there is a question whether we פסקן pasken like רב
Rav or not, but the other point is that nobody would say
you're לא יוצא lo yotzei according to רב אסי, Rav Asi, but
you might be saying it's a really very בדיעבד bedieved type of
fulfillment. Okay, and that's an important חשבון. cheshbon. Like, you know, somebody
says I got to rush off to work. We discussed the other
day that the reading of the מגילה megillah of the morning halachically
really more weighty than the reading at the night. Okay, I know,
but I got to read a rush off to work, so I'll
go to work and then when I come back I'll read it
to myself, right? So here the point would be, you know, that
to appreciate is that a, you know, how to make that type
of a חשבון cheshbon if you really say it's a very בדיעבד
bedieved fulfillment at least according to רב אסי. Rav Asi. Yes.
There's רב Rav and this is I guess technically filled if you
have ten people, well then what about the idea of, you know,
going to the bigger מנין minyan in town and stuff like that?
Right, so that's an interesting question.
Do we, yeah, so certainly they
do that around here.
Right, yeah. I mean there are some opinions about that but I'm
not sure you have to, like everybody is getting the, every reading
of it is being מפרסם mifarsaim it to a רבים rabim and
then you have multiple רבים rabim and sort of like everybody's getting
the message, you
know? So, it's a good, it's a good question about
whether there are פוסקים poskim that insist that you should. I mean
normally that's framed in the context of like ברוב עם הדרת מלך,
b'rov am hadras melech, that it's a more and even in the
context of ברוב עם הדרת מלך b'rov am hadras melech we don't
pay attention to that and we've had a long history of, you
know, having multiple different מניינים minyanim and choices and so on. But
here you want to say in addition to the normal ברוב עם,
b'rov am, there's maybe a greater sense of פרסום הנס pirsum hanes
when it's a larger community all at once rather than multiple parallel
communities. Okay, so now I have a lot of things I need
to look up. Okay,
I vaguely remember that there's some discussion about that but I have
to double check.
Question before going to the next משנה. Mishnah. On the first day
we were discussing about days and the 15th sometimes does fall out
on שבת Shabbos in our calendar, and none of us knew what
the correct practice is in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Yeah, it's you separate these things out and oh, that's reminding me
about the, about the משלוח מנות mishloach manos days about, about
משולש, meshulash, right, because, right, right, right. I said it incorrectly before.
Right, because what you do in ירושלים Yerushalayim by פורים משולש Purim
meshulash is you read מגילה megillah early and you have מתנות לאביונים
matanos l'evyonim early.
Is it on Friday?
And the 15th is on שבת. Shabbos. So you read מגילה megillah
early, right, you have the סעודה seuda on שבת Shabbos and you
do the משלוח מנות mishloach manos on Sunday. So I actually misspoke
that it's and that's even though it's a walled city. But certainly
when you're מקדימים makdimim because of not the village case, in the
village case, right, you know, that what I was saying would be
correct, if you were the villagers would go back to a Monday
then they would have the סעודה seuda and the משלוח מנות mishloach
manos on the same day. But when you're going back because of
שבת, Shabbos, then you put the משלוח מנות mishloach manos the day
after.
So even though משלוח מנות mishloach manos is
about the סעודה, seuda, kind
of connected to it.
Yeah, I know, I know. But that answers, I'm going to double
check all of this, but that answers David's question if that's correct
about the issue that משלוח מנות mishloach manos is about sending things,
so what are you doing? So right, so you keep משלוח מנות
mishloach manos with the סעודה seuda when you're going early because like
you're the villager and the normal day is a non-שבת Shabbos day,
but the normal day is a שבת Shabbos day, you know, that's
what they do now in ירושלים Yerushalayim and they have three, they
have it Friday is the קריאה, keriah, שבת Shabbos is the סעודה
seuda and the משלוח מנות mishloach manos is Sunday. Thanks. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איזו עיר גדולה, Eizu
ir gedola, what is a big city? כל שיש בה עשרה בטלנים,
Kol sheyesh ba asara batlanim, we saw that before. You need ten
people that are sitting around not doing anything. Ten people that are
in the שול shul ready to make a מנין. minyan. Otherwise it's
not a big city, it would be a village and it would
get pushed back to the market day. פחות מכאן הרי זה כפר.
Pachos mikan harei zeh kfar. Less than this is a village
and gets pushed back. באלו אמרו מקדימין ולא מאחרין. B'eilu amru makdimin
v'lo ma'acharin. So regarding the reading of the מגילה megillah they say
that there are times you'll do it early and not, but you'll
never do it late, right? It never goes, you never do something
like you never do. Never do the 14th later than the 14th
and you never do the 15th later than the 15th. אבל זמן
עצי כהנים והעם Aval zman atzei kohanim veha'am probably some גרסא, girsa,
we just saw this in תענית, Taanit, the the day that people
would have that special holiday of bringing
of bringing wood to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, to תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av and as רש״י Rashi points out other fast days as
well.
חגיגה, Chagigah, as bringing of a קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagigah in normally
you would bring on the first day of יום טוב Yom Tov
but if the first day of יום טוב Yom Tov falls out
on a שבת Shabbat you can't do it
and הקהל, Hakhel, הקהל Hakhel which you would do at the beginning
of a שמטה Shmita cycle on סוכות Sukkot the day after after
סוכות Sukkot but if that's I mean the day after but if
right but if that day falls on actually the day the day
the first day of חול המועד Chol HaMoed of סוכות Sukkot excuse
me not after all of סוכות. Sukkot. So that day falls out
on שבת Shabbat you can't do it, we'll see why in the
גמרא. Gemara. So if all of these things can't be done on
their right day because they fall out on שבת Shabbat and you
don't fast on שבת Shabbat etc. and you wouldn't bring the wood
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash on שבת. Shabbat.
Is it not יום טוב אחרון של חג? Yom Tov acharon shel
chag?
Well if you look on the side they switch the גרסא girsa
to יום טוב ראשון Yom Tov rishon because actually it's okay. But
actually there's some issue about that. Alright so anyway okay anyway all
these cases of so in all of these cases where you have
to push it off so where are we?
מאחרין ולא מקדימין, ma'acharin velo makdimin, you push it off to Sunday
you don't push it earlier to Friday and we'll see why in
the גמרא. Gemara. אף על פי שאמרנו מקדימין Af al pi she'amru
makdimin
now also although they say you read the מגילה Megillah early on
a Thursday and a and a Monday in these villages ולא מאחרין
velo me'acharin מותר בהספד
ובתענית mutar behespeid uv'ta'anit ומתנות לאביונים umatanot l'evyonim and here's the line
מתנות לאביונים matanot l'evyonim is not מותרים mutarim but okay so on
meaning is that's when you do מתנות לאביונים. matanot l'evyonim. So although
you you know you read it earlier right although you read although
you read it early that day itself of reading is not the
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So if you're reading on a Monday or
Thursday and the real 14th falls out I don't know on a
Wednesday and you're reading on a Monday so that Monday it might
be the day of doing the מצוה mitzvah of מקרא מגילה Mikra
Megillah but it's not פורים. Purim. פורים Purim is still Wednesday and
therefore you can have a הספד hespeid and a תענית ta'anit on
that Monday. Okay it's a day where you can have these so
alright let's that's not in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay so the חג
chag of פורים Purim remains on its right day but the early
day of the early day of reading is just the מצוה mitzvah
of reading and does not and therefore does not make it forbidden
to have a הספד hespeid and to do a fast. But like
we said before מתנות לאביונים matanot l'evyonim what you do do together
with the reading is the gifts to the poor. So with the
reading comes the gifts to the poor but does not come the
whole idea of the חג chag of פורים. Purim. The חג chag
of פורים Purim remains בזמנו bizmano in its right date and that's
when the שמחה simcha is. אמר רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yehuda אימתי
eimatai אימתי eimatai
when is it true that the villagers read earlier? מקום שנכנסים בשני
ובחמישי Makom shenichnasim b'sheini uv'chamishi if these villagers actually come into the
town on Monday and Thursday. אבל מקום שאין נכנסים Aval makom she'ein
nichnasim but if it's a scenario where you have villagers but they
don't come into the towns on Mondays and Thursdays so מקום שאין
נכנסים makom she'ein nichnasim לא בשני ולא בחמישי lo b'sheini velo b'chamishi
אין קורין אותה אלא בזמנה ein korin otah ela bizmanah then we
don't allow them to read early the whole point of reading early
is because they're coming into the towns on those days. Okay so
a lot of things here about wrapping up this idea about reading
earlier in the villages. So back to the גמרא Gemara I mean
to the גמרא. Gemara. תנא עשרה בטלנים שבבית הכנסת. Tana asarah batlanim
shebbebeit haknesset. So עשרה בטלנים asarah batlanim means ten people hanging around
in שול shul you know to be available for a מנין. minyan.
The idea about being a מנין minyan man or whatever already has
a very long history.
בטלנים Batlanim that sounds like a negative.
Yeah I know but it means like readily available to you know
they're sitting around they're כולל kollel guys that are there in the
שול. shul. What? Maybe maybe it means retired. Okay if רש״י Rashi
says שהן בטלים ממלאכתן shehen beteilim mimmilachtan if you look at רש״י
Rashi הם לא עושים שום עבודה וניזונים משל ציבור כדי להיות מצויים
בתפילה בבית הכנסת. venizonim mishel tzibbur kedei lihyot metzuyim bitfillah b'veit haknesset.
רש״י Rashi explains it completely as like you're paid to to not
work so that you're always available to make a מנין. minyan. So
there's this joke I don't know how funny it is there's this
joke this guy appears before a judge you know whatever he's giving
testimony so they say state your name and profession. So he says
you know whatever he says
יאנקל פרנק Yankel Frank and I'm a מנין minyan man. So the
judge says what's a מנין minyan man? So he says well you
know they give me a salary and when they have nine men
and they need a tenth so so they call me up. So
the judge says says that's crazy says I could do that. So
he looks at the judge and says oh you're a ייד Yid
too huh? Anyway bada boom. Okay so moving on. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this. באלו אמרו Ba'elu amru what where are we? Sorry I'm sorry
באלו אמרו מקדימין ולא מאחרין ba'elu amru makdimin velo me'acharin מאי טעמא
mai ta'ama what's the reason? אמר רבי אבא בר שמואל אמר קרא
Amar Rabbi Abba bar Shmuel amar krah ולא יעבור. velo ya'avor. Okay
so it can't be later. אמר רבי אבא בר שמואל מנין שאין
מונין ימים ושנים Amar Rabbi Abba bar Shmuel minayin she'ein monin yamim
v'shanim since we had a statement of רבי אבא בר שמואל Rabbi
Abba bar Shmuel we say a different statement of רבי אבא בר
שמואל. Rabbi Abba bar Shmuel. How do you know that you don't
count days when it comes to years? Years are measured in months,
not days. שנאמר she-ne'emar לחדשי השנה. le-chodshei ha-shana. חדשים אתה מונה לשנים
ואי אתה מונה ימים לשנים. chadashim ata moneh le-shanim ve-ee ata moneh
yamim le-shanim. So years are counted by months, not days. I'll say
what this means in a
minute. ורבנן דקיסרי משמיה דרבי אבא אמרו, ve-rabbanan di-keisari mishmei de-Rabbi Abba
amru, and the Rabbis of Caesarea said in the name of Rabbi
Abba: מנין שאין מחשבין שעות לחדשים? minayin she-ein mechashvin sha'ot le-chodashim? How
do you know you don't measure months by hours? You measure them
by days. שנאמר she-ne'emar עד חודש ימים, ad chodesh yamim, until the
month of days. ימים אתה מחשב לחדשים ואי אתה מחשב שעות לחדשים.
yamim ata mechashev le-chodashim ve-ee ata mechashev sha'ot le-chodashim. You count days
to months and not hours to months. What does this mean? So
Rashi says the case is, for example, somebody takes a vow that
they're not going to eat something for a whole year. And now
it's the third of Sivan. So how do you measure a year?
So you measure a year until the second of Sivan. You measure
it by sort of the day of the month and you do
not measure it by days. You don't say, no, a year is
354 days, a lunar year, or so years 365 days. So if
you say you're not going to eat it for a year, that
means
354, 365, though you don't
use, you don't go by days, you go by months, which means
like the day of the month. Similarly, if you say I'm not
going to eat this thing for a month, you say a month
is till the same, the same date or one day before that
in the next month. You don't say, no, a month is 29
and a half days, and you measure a month by hours, it's
29 days and 12 hours. So you don't measure these by hours,
you measure them
by, by days. Okay. אבל זמן עצי כהנים ותשעה באב וחגיגה והקהל,
aval zman atzei kohanim ve-tisha b'av ve-chagiga ve-hakhel, מאחרין ולא מקדימין. ma'acharin
ve-lo makdimin. Just one sec, just give me one second.
I just need to answer this, I'm sorry for one
second. Okay. Alright, so, sorry, back to this. Okay. זמן עצי כהנים
ותשעה באב וחגיגה והקהל מאחרין ולא מקדימין. zman atzei kohanim ve-tisha b'av
ve-chagiga ve-hakhel ma'acharin ve-lo makdimin. These things you can do later, not
earlier. So the Gemara says: תשעה באב אקדמויי פורענותא לא מקדמי. tisha
b'av akdumei puranuta lo makdimi. Why, why don't you do Tisha B'av
earlier? You don't want to start bringing in the bad things, the
things that evoke all of the bad events, and go early, like
let's do the fast earlier. No, these are things that we're supposed
to want to be pushing off, want to be sort of showing
obviously our reluctance about
them. You know, they're bad days. חגיגה והקהל, chagiga ve-hakhel, why do
you do Chagiga and Hakhel later rather than earlier? משום דקדם להו
זמן חיובא. mishum di-kdem lehu zman chiyuva. Because the obligation doesn't come.
Chagiga you only bring during the chag, you don't bring it before
the chag, and Hakhel presumably the obligation only begins after the chag
is out and it doesn't begin earlier, so somehow there's a sense
that once the obligation began, it could be done a little bit
later, but before the obligation began, you cannot do it. And Rashi
says the same is true about the idea of atzei kohanim. I
think it's a little tautologous: why do we make an assumption that
if it's not on the date it can be later than the
date but not earlier than the date? But somehow that's the idea.
All right. תנא חגיגה וכל זמן חגיגה מאחרין. tana chagiga ve-chol zman
chagiga ma'acharin.
So the Chagiga and the entire time of Chagiga you can postpone.
So the Gemara says: מאי היא? mai hi? What does that mean?
בשלמא חגיגה דאי מיקלע בשבת מאחרין ליה לבתר שבת. bishlama chagiga de-ee
mikla be-shabbat ma'acharin lei le-vatar shabbat.
I understand what it means to postpone Chagiga. If it comes on
Shabbat we postpone it till Sunday. אלא זמן חגיגה מאי? ela zman
chagiga mai? What does it mean you postpone the time of the
Chagiga? So אמר רב אושעיא הכי קאמר, amar Rav Oshaya hachi ka'amar,
here's what it means: חגיגה בשבת. chagiga be-shabbat. There are two scenarios
you'll push things off. Number one is the Chagiga falls out on
Shabbat, if the first day of Yom Tov falls out on Shabbat,
and number two, ועולת ראיה, ve-olat re'iyah, if the olah that you
also bring on Yom Tov, okay, over the chag, that אפילו ביום
טוב דזמן חגיגה הוא, afilu be-yom tov de-zman chagiga hu, even when
the, even in a normal scenario that the Yom Tov is the
first day of Yom Tov is not Shabbat, but nevertheless it's a,
and the first day of Yom Tov is a day where you
could bring the Chagiga, it's not a day where you could bring
the olah, and therefore the olah will always be not on the
first day of Yom Tov. מאחרין. ma'acharin. So it's a very complicated
way of saying you never bring the olat re'iyah on the first
day of Yom Tov. Although the first day of Yom Tov is
a זמן חגיגה, zman chagiga, it's not a זמן עולה, zman olah,
and therefore you will always do it on not on the first
day.
Why is that?
Because Chagiga you eat the meat and therefore you can do something
for אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, olah you don't eat the meat. That's
right. So the Gemara says: ומני בית שמאי היא? u-mani Beit Shammai
hi? And who is this? It's Beit Shammai. דתנן בית שמאי אומרים
מביאים שלמים ביום טוב ואין סומכין עליהם אבל לא עולות. de-tnan Beit
Shammai omrim mevi'im shlamim be-yom tov ve-ein somchin aleihem aval lo olot.
You can bring shlamim on Yom Tov, you don't do smicha, we
won't get into that, but you don't bring olot because you don't
eat from them even if it's an olat re'iyah. ובית הלל אומרים
מביאים שלמים ועולות וסומכין עליהם. u-Beit Hillel omrim mevi'im shlamim ve-olot ve-somchin
aleihem. You can even bring an olat re'iyah, it's a tzorach of
the Yom Tov and you can bring. Wow.
רבא אמר, Rava amar,
yeah we did all that in Beitzah. רבא אמר חגיגה כל זמן
חגיגה מאחרין. Rava amar chagiga kol zman chagiga ma'acharin. Now Rava says
a much easier read: you can postpone the Chagiga for the duration
of the time of the Chagiga, for the duration of Yom Tov,
בתר הכי לא, vatar hachi lo, you can't bring a Chagiga after
Yom Tov. דתנן, de-tnan, we taught in the Mishnah, meaning after the
whole chag. Right, so you can postpone it from the first day
to one of the other days of the חג, chag, you can
do it in a later זמן חגיגה, zman chagiga, but you can't
do it later than the חג. chag. דתנן de'tnan we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, מי שלא חג ביום טוב ראשון של חג, mi
shelo chag b'yom tov rishon shel chag, if you didn't bring the
חגיגה chagiga on the first day, חוגג והולך כל הרגל כולו וביום
טוב האחרון של חג, chogeg v'holech kol ha'regel kulo u'v'yom tov ha'acharon
shel chag, you do it the entire רגל regel up through the
last, up through the last day, but you don't do it later
than the last day. So you can only be מאחרין ma'achrin if
you're still during זמן חגיגה. zman chagiga. עבר הרגל ולא חג, avar
ha'regel v'lo chag, and if the entire רגל regel passed and you
didn't bring your חגיגה, chagiga, אינו חייב באחריותו, eino chayav b'achrayuso, so
you're done. You're not obligated to bring it, but you also weren't
יוצא. yotzei. There's no you're not able to do it. רבא אמר
חגיגה וכל זמן חגיגה מאחרין. Rava amar chagiga v'chol zman chagiga ma'achrin.
The point of saying you can postpone it the entire read it
like רבא, Rava, you can bring the חגיגה chagiga late but only
during the זמן חגיגה, zman chagiga, but to tell you even a
bigger חידוש chiddush that you have the זמן חגיגה, zman chagiga, you
have a seven day period to bring it ואפילו בעצרת, v'afilu b'atzeret,
even by עצרת, atzeret, even though שבועות Shavuos is a one day,
you could be מאחרין ma'achrin the חגיגה chagiga if you didn't bring
it. If the first day יום טוב Yom Tov was שבת Shabbos
or שבועות Shavuos was שבת, Shabbos, you could be מאחרין ma'achrin it
and you have כל זמן חגיגה, kol zman chagiga, a whole seven
days to bring it, or six more days. ואפילו עצרת דחד יומא
מאחרין דתנן מודין בית שמאי ובית הלל דאם חל עצרת להיות בשבת
שיום טבוח אחר שבת, v'afilu atzeret d'chad yoma ma'achrin de'tnan modin Beis
Shammai u'Beis Hillel d'im chal atzeret lihyos b'Shabbos she'yom tivoach achar Shabbos,
that even though it's no longer שבועות, Shavuos, the day of slaughtering
is Sunday, that you can still bring it. There's an idea that,
you know, the six days after שבועות Shavuos are still days which
paralleling the other חגים chagim which you can bring a חגיגה chagiga
which still connect to the חג. chag. Okay, let's just again turn
the page. We're gonna have to catch up
sometime. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא רבי נטע נטיעה בפורים ורחץ
בקרונה של ציפורי בשבעה עשר בתמוז. amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Chanina,
Rabbi nata netiah b'Purim v'rachatz b'kronah shel Tzipori b'shivah asar b'Tammuz. So
there you go, relates to yesterday. רבי Rabbi number one did a
planting on פורים. Purim. This is going to get to the issue
of is פורים Purim אסור בעשיית מלאכה. assur b'asiyas melacha. Number two
is he literally he bathed in the like wagon area, like in
the wagons of ציפורי Tzipori on שבעה עשר בתמוז, shivah asar b'Tammuz,
just means in public like hopefully the whatever, he went into the
bathhouse in public in ציפורי Tzipori on שבעה עשר בתמוז shivah asar
b'Tammuz to show that although it is a תענית, ta'anis, you don't
have any of the other עינויים, inuim, right? Yesterday you could have
taken a shower, you could have done all the other things that
you can't do on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. So he did that to sort of publicly make that
statement. וביקש לעקור תשעה באב ולא הודו לו. u'vikeish la'akor Tisha B'Av
v'lo hodu lo. And he actually wanted to just get rid of
תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, but they didn't agree to him. So that's
crazy! Why would he want to get rid of תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av and how is he able to get rid of תשעה באב?
Tisha B'Av? So תוספות Tosafos reads it to mean he doesn't literally
want to get rid of תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, maybe he wanted
to make תשעה באב Tisha B'Av on the tenth of אב, Av,
because if you remember we learned at the end of תענית Taanis
that there's reasons to argue that it should have been the tenth
of אב. Av. But anyway it's a pretty drastic statement. So we'll
just read one line about this in the גמרא, Gemara, or
not the גמרא, Gemara, the end of this ברייתא. braisa. אמר לפניו
רבי אבא בר זבדא רבי לאו כך היה מעשה. amar lefanav Rabbi
Abba bar Zavda, Rabbi lo kach hayah ma'aseh. רבי, Rabbi, that wasn't
what happened. It wasn't that he tried to completely uproot תשעה באב.
Tisha B'Av. אלא תשעה באב שחל להיות בשבת הוה. ela Tisha B'Av
she'chal lihyos b'Shabbos havah. It was a specific case for תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av fell out on שבת Shabbos ודחינוהו לאחר שבת, v'dachinuhu l'achar
Shabbos,
and we were going to like the משנה Mishnah says postpone it
to the tenth ואמר רבי v'amar Rabbi and to Sunday and רבי
Rabbi said you know what הואיל ונדחה ידחה ho'il v'nidcha yidcha since
we're anyway you know not having תשעה באב Tisha B'Av on the
right day we might as well not do it. So he actually
in one year when it fell on שבת Shabbos that was the
year he wanted to not have it. He didn't want to permanently
get rid of it. But if you're not doing it on the
right day just forget about it. ולא הודו חכמים v'lo hodu chachamim
and the Rabbis did not agree to him. No kidding. So קרא
עליה kari aleih so who was it that originally said this statement?
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in the name of רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
said back to רבי אבא בר זבדא Rabbi Abba bar Zavda who
you know remembered the story differently, טובים השנים מן האחד. tovim ha'shnayim
min ha'echad.
So two is better than one. Without you around I would have
completely misremembered what this event was with רבי, Rabbi, you helped me
remember correctly that it was a particular case of תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av that fell out on שבת. Shabbos. We'll pick up with this
tomorrow in the discussion of really the first line which is the
fact that he made a planting on פורים, Purim, is פורים Purim
אסור בעשיית מלאכה assur b'asiyas melacha or not? So for that we
will see tomorrow.
What was it about רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar to make him say
that?
That לאו כך היה מעשה? lo kach hayah ma'aseh? No the original
version, the original version, oh what he says, oh
so he can't, right,
טובים השנים מן האחד, tovim ha'shnayim min ha'echad, he accepted your position.
Right, so why did
he what did
they do to him to make him say that?
Oh got it. All right.
Question about walled city. Are there any walled cities today where we
have this, so ירושלים Yerushalayim we read on the fifteenth. Yeah. Are
there any other cities that read it by that?
Yeah, we'll talk about that, sure, in today's דף, daf, but we'll
talk about that tomorrow. Okay, great, thanks.